Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov,
we pick up we're about a daf דף daf behind, we'll see
how far we get, but anyway we pick up today on daf
vav דף ו daf vav and we are on the middle of
daf vav דף ו daf vav with Tanya Abba Binyamin תניא אבא
בנימין. Tanya Abba Binyamin. So we have been doing a list of
statements in the name of Abba Binyamin אבא בנימין. Abba Binyamin. We
had done a famous one about the mazikim מזיקים mazikim and now
we pick up with Tanya תניא Tanya Abba Binyamin אבא בנימין Abba
Binyamin about twenty lines down beginning of a long line right right
where it says Malachim alef chet מלכים א ח Malachim Alef Chet
in that margin between the Gemara גמרא Gemara and Rashi רש"י, Rashi,
it's one line above that. Tanya תניא, Tanya, we've taught in a
Baraita ברייתא, Baraita, Abba Binyamin omer אבא בנימין אומר, Abba Binyamin omer,
ein tfilato shel adam nishmaat ela b'beit haknesset אין תפלתו של אדם
נשמעת אלא בבית הכנסת. ein tfilato shel adam nishmaat ela b'beit haknesset.
A person's prayer is only heard, not only but meant that phrase
ein ella אין אלא ein ella means like primarily it's heard, in
the best heard, thank you, in the synagogue. Shenemar שנאמר, Shenemar, lishmoa
el harina v'el hatefilla לשמוע אל הרינה ואל התפילה, lishmoa el harina
v'el hatefilla, to listen to the rejoicing, to the exaltation and the
prayer.
B'makom rina sham t'hei tfillah במקום רינה שם תהא תפילה, B'makom rina
sham t'hei tfillah, in the place of exalting, in the place of
singing, there should be the prayer. Now the significance of this statement
is twofold. First of all as I've mentioned to you, there, you
know, the rabbis were not in charge of the shuls שולן shuls
in the time of the Gemara גמרא Gemara and of the Mishnah
משנה, Mishnah, clearly, and also archaeological evidence to support that there was
a different leadership. The rabbis attended the synagogues but it wasn't like
you were the rabbi of a synagogue and it wasn't like there
was some direct relationship there. There's actually a different leadership of the
synagogues as a separate institution than sort of the rabbis and their
endeavors in the Beit HaMidrash בית המדרש. Beit HaMidrash. So first of
all there's like a general as I told you question about the
relationship between sort of prayer and Talmud Torah תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
and investing time in one, investing time in the other, different ways
of connecting to God. There's also a whole question about sort of
the Beit Haknesset בית הכנסת Beit Haknesset which obviously was very central
as an obligation but you know how does that relate to the
Beit HaMidrash בית המדרש? Beit HaMidrash? And sometimes we actually hear about
the obligation to daven דאוון, daven, a person's prayer is heard if
he davens דאוונט davens where he learns, not in the Beit Haknesset
בית הכנסת. Beit Haknesset. So there's always a little bit of a
although this is obvious so of course you're supposed to daven דאוון
daven in shul שול, shul, first of all maybe not, maybe you
daven דאוון daven at home and this isn't necessarily saying that it's
preferable to daven דאוון daven in a minyan מניין. minyan. This is
saying forget the minyan מניין, minyan, should I have a minyan מניין
minyan in my house, should I have a minyan מניין minyan in
shul שול, shul, should I daven דאוון daven by myself at my
house, should I daven דאוון daven by myself in shul שול. shul.
This is about location, it isn't about minyan מניין. minyan. And it's
also not self-evident that this is the best location because there's other
Gemaras גמרות Gemaras that talk about the place where you learn. But
anyway so that's sort of the context of why this statement is
significant and within that context it is saying it's best to daven
דאוון daven in the synagogue, why? Because that's where there is rina
רינה, rina, which is interesting, what does that mean that's where there
is rina רינה? rina? Clearly that's something different than tfillah תפילה. tfillah.
So Rashi רש"י Rashi says, if you look at Rashi רש"י, Rashi,
he says, Beit Haknesset shesham omrim hatzibur shirot v'tishbachot b'ne'imat kol arev
בית הכנסת ששם אומרים הציבור שירות ותשבחות בנעימת קול ערב. Beit Haknesset
shesham omrim hatzibur shirot v'tishbachot b'ne'imat kol arev. That's where you say
the prayers, right, with nice singing, nice, you know, it's very musical,
it's much better you do it with the whole tzibur ציבור. tzibur.
A lot of people haven't
read that Rashi רש"י Rashi lately.
Right, there's good there's nice beautiful music and singing when you do
it in a tzibur ציבור tzibur and that is something that here
is being praised as a very important lead in or accompaniment to
the act phenomenon of prayer and the way in which it sort
of maybe if you would engages people, the sense of rina רינה.
rina. And also the Maharsha מהרש"א Maharsha points out that the same
way we do, you know, we start Shmoneh Esrei שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei with shevach v'tishbacha שבח ותשבחה shevach v'tishbacha and we start with
P'sukei D'zimra פסוקי דזמרה P'sukei D'zimra of singing, that there's an idea
that before you go into what's seen as central tfillah תפילה, tfillah,
which is the bakasha בקשה bakasha and making requests of God, it
starts by praising and singing and so on, you know, about singing
about God's greatness and that also sort of a similar context here.
So yes and if you also think about what we were mentioning
earlier, especially if you're trying to plan this after Beit HaMikdash בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash where you had the Shirat HaLevi'im שירת הלווים Shirat
HaLevi'im with musical instruments and the whole so we're trying to sort
of recreate that experience, especially say the Beit Knesses Mikdash Me'at בית
כנסת מקדש מעט Beit Knesses Mikdash Me'at absolutely makes a lot of
sense to say something like that.
Right, absolutely, very well said. Okay so now the Gemara גמרא Gemara
goes on, amar Rabin bar Rav Adda amar Rabbi Yitzchak minayin shehakadosh
baruch hu matzuy b'beit haknesset אמר רבין בר רב אדא אמר רבי
יצחק מניין שהקדוש ברוך הוא מצוי בבית הכנסת. amar Rabin bar Rav
Adda amar Rabbi Yitzchak minayin shehakadosh baruch hu matzuy b'beit haknesset. And
now we're going to go on sort of talking about the importance
of the Beit Haknesset בית הכנסת. Beit Haknesset. How do you know
God is found in the Beit Haknesset בית הכנסת? Beit Haknesset? Shenemar
שנאמר, Shenemar, Elohim nitzav b'adat el אלהים נצב בעדת אל. Elohim nitzav
b'adat el. God is standing in the community of God, the community
of people that have gathered for God and adat עדת adat is
where we learn the idea of a minyan מניין minyan from, we
learn from Korah קרח Korah that there were ten and therefore God
is present there, God is standing there, maybe even God is sort
of waiting for people to arrive there we'll see in a minute.
So uminayin l'asara ומניין לעשרה uminayin l'asara
now of course that doesn't exactly indicate you know that that's a
minyan מניין minyan idea, that's not necessarily a Beit Haknesset בית הכנסת
Beit Haknesset idea. So the next line really says the minyan מניין.
minyan. Uminayin l'asara shemitpallelim sheshechina imahem ומניין לעשרה שמתפללים ששכינה עמהם. Uminayin
l'asara shemitpallelim sheshechina imahem. How do you know when ten people pray,
presumably wherever they pray, wherever there's a minyan מניין, minyan, God is
with them? Shenemar שנאמר, Shenemar, Elohim nitzav b'adat el אלהים נצב בעדת
אל. Elohim nitzav b'adat el. God is present in the congregation of
God. So the other wasn't about there being a minyan מניין, minyan,
the other was just about it being a Beit Haknesset בית הכנסת.
Beit Haknesset. So Rashi רש"י Rashi says, Beit El בית אל Beit
El in the first reading, adat El עדת אל adat El was
b'beit moed בבית מועד. b'beit moed. So that's maybe a little circular
because he's there, he's the place where he visits. But anyway, בית
bayit, מועד *beit moed* also אהל מועד *ohel moed* as Michael just
said, that sense of the בית כנסת beit knesset *beit knesset* being
a type of a מקדש מעט *mikdash ma'at*. So here reading even
without there being a מנין minyan, *minyan*, this is the without a
בית bayit המקדש *beit hamikdash*, this is the place now that is
the place of God's dwelling, that God inhabits. And then we move
on from that to the idea of a מנין minyan, *minyan*, and
now we're going to go through a discourse, through a list of
things which you might be very well familiar with, it's really a
משנה *mishnah* in פרקי אבות *pirkei avot*. So let's take a look.
So, that's ten people where besides בית כנסת beit knesset. *beit knesset*
where ten people דאוון davven, *daven* God is present, ומנין לשלושה שיושבים
בדין שהשכינה עמהם *u'minayin l'shlosha sheyoshvim b'din she'Shechina imahem*? How do you
know when three sit in judgment that God is with them? שנאמר
shenemar, בקרב אלוהים ישפוט *shene'emar b'kerev Elohim yishpot*, in the presence of
God they shall judge, and judgment is with a בית דין Beis
Din *beit din* of three, and so therefore God is present with
a בית bayit דין *beit din* of three. ומנין לשנים שיושבים ועוסקים
בתורה שהשכינה עמהם *u'minayin l'shnayim sheyoshvim v'oskim baTorah she'Shechina imahem*? And how
do you know when two people sit and learn תורה Torah *Torah*
God is with them? שנאמר shene'emar: *shene'emar*, as it says, אז נדברו
יראי השם איש אל רעהו *az nidberu yirei Hashem ish el re'ehu*,
then those who feared God spoke one to his fellow, ויקשב השם
וישמע *vayakshev Hashem vayishma*, and God heard and he listened, ויכתב ספר
זכרון *vayikatev sefer zikaron*, and he wrote it in the book of
remembrance. Okay, מאי ולחושבי שמו *mai v'lechoshvei shemo*?
And the end of the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* ends what?
Yeah, no, I'm saying the end of the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*, ויראי השם ולחושבי שמו *v'yirei Hashem u'lechoshvei shemo*, those who feared
God and those who sort of, you know, consider his name. אמר
רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi, *amar Rav Ashi*: חשב אדם *chashav adam*...
so this is completely parenthetical, it's taken from another גמרא Gemara *gemara*,
but it was the end of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, it's not
part of our theme. But nevertheless, חשב אדם לעשות מצוה mitzvah, ונאנס
ולא עשאה *chashav adam la'asot mitzvah v'ne'enas v'lo asah*, if a person
intended to do a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* and was נאנס *ne'enas*, he
was sort of, you know,
circumstances made it impossible although he was really attempting to do it,
nevertheless מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו עשאה *ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu asah*. So
it's ולחושבי שמו *u'lechoshvei shemo*, as long as you're planning that's enough.
Now of course the גמרא Gemara *gemara* makes a very good point,
it's not just enough to plan, we have million thoughts in our
head, it's נאנס *ne'enas*, you were really trying and somehow it became
impossible, right? Circumstances made it impossible. But if there was a real
attempt to do something, God, you still get credit for it. That's
okay, but that was parenthetical. Back to our theme though. ומנין שאפילו
אחד echad שיושב ועוסק בתורה שהשכינה עמו *u'minayin she'afillu echad sheyoshev v'osek
baTorah she'Shechina imo*? Back to the theme, how do you know even
not only three or two, but even one person sits and learns
תורה Torah. *Torah* that God is with him? שנאמר Shene'emar, *shene'emar*: בכל
המקום אשר Asher, אזכיר את שמי אבוא אליך וברכתיך *b'chol hamakom asher
azkir et shemi avo elecha u'verachticha*, any place where I will mention
my name,
I will come to you in the singular and bless you. So
of course this is always a funny פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* because we
read it to say wherever you mention my name, but that's not
what the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* says. It says wherever I mention my
name, I will come and bless you, which might be referring to
like a place that God has chosen or designated or sanctified. But
here we are reading it like that if you are learning there,
then God has sort of allowed his name to be mentioned there
or through you God has caused his name to be called out
there, and then God will come and bless.
Now you notice that's not דאוונינג *davening*, mentioning God's name.
I know, so that's a good, very good point. You're right, I
mean the earlier פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* was נדברו יראי השם *nidberu yirei
Hashem*, here it's אזכיר את שמי *azkir et shemi*, and the context
often about being מזכיר שם השם *mazkir shem Hashem*, like the ברכת
כהנים *Birkat Kohanim*, right? ושמו את שמי על בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael,
*v'samu et shemi al bnei Yisrael*, you know, it's a sense of...
you're right, you could have very much interpreted it as דאוונינג *davening*,
and you're right, it really is just through the חז"ל Chazal. *Chazal's*
lens that they see this as talking about תורה Torah, *Torah*. It's
worth mentioning in that context though, that this משנה *mishnah* in פרקי
אבות *pirkei avot* is all about תורה Torah *Torah*. And here we've
moved from different modes, and the גמרא Gemara *gemara's* actually going to
point that out. From תפילה tefillah *tefillah* ten, to three דין *din*,
and then to תורה Torah *Torah* at the end. So what is
the whole sense of moving to different modes? So to one degree
it's sort of acknowledging a lot of different ways in which one
sort of connects to God, and there's also, you know, this ongoing
sort of question going back to this tension between תפילה *tefillah* and
שמונה עשרה Asara, *Shmoneh Esrei* of maybe seeing, you know, everything as
a type of a תפילה *tefillah*. So going back to Michael's point,
like if, you know, maybe learning... you're... how much are we saying
God's name as we're learning? Now that we're doing a lot of
אגדתא aggadata *aggadata*, yes, we say it more. But normally you would
sort of say God's name a lot less when you learn than
when you דאוון *daven*. But to see that as another way of
invoking God's name and all of these are ways sort of of,
you know, that they can also sort of like different forms of
essentially bringing God and connecting to God, you know, in this world.
So it is true that this could have been read as תפילה
*tefillah*, but it is here being read as תורה Torah *Torah*. And
now the גמרא Gemara *gemara* asks what's the idea of progression? כי
מאחר דאפילו אחד echad. *ki me'achar d'afillu echad*, if it's even for
even one person that this, you know, God comes and is present,
תרי מבעיא *trei mibaya*? Of course it's true, why did you have
to quote me the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* about two? So the גמרא
Gemara *gemara* says: תרי מכתבן מליהו בספר זכרונות *trei michtevan milayhu b'sefer
zichronot*.
Two, it says that God listens and he hears and he writes
it down in the book of remembrance. חד לא מכתבן מליהו בספר
זכרונות *chad lo michtevan milayhu b'sefer zichronot*. One it doesn't get written
down in the book of remembrance. Now what exactly does that mean
get written down in the book of remembrance? Like if it means
are you going to get rewarded for your deeds, presumably you'll always
get rewarded for your deeds, two or one, what difference does it
make? So the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* has a nice idea. He says
when you're learning תורה Torah. *Torah* with two people, it helps correct
mistakes, right? Because you have somebody to bounce it off of, they
argue back, you think through better. So he says there, when you
come up with a conclusion in your learning, God writes it down
because it's like whatever you conclude is like worth remembering, it's a
better sense of being more accurate, you know, that you come to
a greater truth. If you're learning by yourself, could be, you know,
it's a lot of interesting thoughts but maybe nothing is really like
exactly on target. So it doesn't get, it doesn't get recorded for,
meaning your merit gets recorded but exactly the ideas you came up
with aren't necessarily worth recording. But anyway, clearly the point is that
there's a greater level as we know in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*,
the learning between two exactly for that reason is ultimately the best
form of learning. Yes.
Is there a distinction being made here in terms of subjectivity or
intellectuality?
So yeah, that's I think, thank you, that's sort of what I
was getting at without not framing it that way, but with the
whole context about the sort of the eliding, the smooshing from תפילה
*Tefillah* to תורה Torah *Torah* and bringing it all together. You're right,
very much is it being framed as, you know, as a religious
activity, it's always a religious activity in the sense that it's a
מצוה mitzvah, *Mitzvah*, but I think what you mean is sort of
at sort of at the personal, you know,
in the from our at the experiential level, sort of we're experiencing
it as a connection to God and not just as some as
an intellectual activity and as almost a type of תפילה *Tefillah*. So
yes.
Does the intellectual activity better with two with more people?
Uh-huh, so you're saying with one person it has...
With one person it could be a spiritual activity like תפילה *Tefillah*
could be.
Uh-huh, that's a nice point and that's the shift to אז נדברו
*Az Nidberu*. Oh, that's a very nice point. Okay, thank you. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues it says like this, okay, so
that's the difference between one and two. If
for two people it gets written down, תלתא מבעיא *tlata miba'ei*, of
course three! And then, you know, what does three make it better?
So מהו דתימא דינא *mahu deteima dina*, no, when three we didn't
say learning תורה Torah *Torah*, three we said, you know, sitting in
דין *Din*, doing a handling of a court case, right? I might
think דין *Din*, law, שלמא דעלמא הוא *shelama de'alma hu*, that's just,
you know, keeping the peace, that's just helping society run smoothly. It's
not תורה Torah, *Torah*, and ולא אתי שכינה *velo ati Shechinah*, and
God isn't present for that. קמשמע לן *kamashma lan* דינא נמי הוי
תורה Torah, *dina nami havei Torah*. Now before we were talking about
תורה Torah, *Torah* being a type of תפילה *Tefillah*, being maybe part
of a subtext here. Here, it seems shifting it the other way,
everything is a type of תורה Torah *Torah*. So דין *Din*, you
know, it's funny, right? Because, you know, on the one hand, when
we learn laws about torts or whatever, all these laws about בית
דין *Beis Din*, we very much think in our mind, yeah, you
know, who's on a בית דין *Beis Din*? Like תלמידי חכמים *Talmidei
Chachamim*, it's applied תורה Torah *Torah*. But, you know, very often the
real people that sit on the court and that really are doing,
you know, the rabbis are off, the תלמידי חכמים *Talmidei Chachamim* are
off in the בית מדרש *Beis Medrash* and other people are dealing
with the real issues about the day-to-day and dealing with court cases
and so on. So here it's saying, no, you should not have
that dichotomy, you know, דין *Din*, this also is תורה Torah *Torah*.
Why is it also תורה Torah, *Torah*? Again, maybe it's תורה *Torah*
because in order to be a good judge, you have to know
תורה *Torah*, because you know if you have to be דן *dan*,
you have to be a דיין *dayan*, you have to know all
of the relevant הלכה halachic *Halacha*. So just straightforwardly that way, but
also maybe the other sense, you know, it sort of is that
תורה *Torah* is not just about being in the בית מדרש *Beis
Medrash*, תורה *Torah* is not just about this intellectual activity and learning
all the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* so now I can sit on a
court case, but actually bringing it into the real world and having
it function in the way it's supposed to function, which is really
creating a better society and a more just society, that's sort of
תורה *Torah* actualized. So it's not just about the process of learning
that goes into giving דין *Din*, it's actually the sense of actualized,
דין *Din* is really actualized תורה *Torah*.
I just find it interesting rather than שלמא דעלמא הוא *shelama de'alma
hu* and then therefore God isn't present when there's peace among the
Jewish people.
Well, exactly,
you could say more likely that God is...
Right, I understand. I mean, but it is true that some people
definitely think that way, you know, ah yeah whatever, you go, you
run society, whatever, I'm going to sit here, the real religious activity
is what gets done in the synagogue or the בית מדרש *Beis
Medrash*. Everything else, although it's obviously critical for everybody's well-being, right, is
not real תורה *Torah*, is not real עבודת השם *Avodas Hashem*. So
that's exactly what this is coming to say with
the conclusion of תורה נמי האי *Torah nami hai*.
Yeah, you could have, you could have. Okay.
So, I mean look, the very way I believe that the טור
*Tur* opens חושן משפט *Choshen Mishpat* is with the מדרש *Midrash* that
says, you know, anybody that is עושה דין לאמיתו *oseh din l'amito*
is כאילו נעשה שותף להקדוש ברוך הוא במעשה בראשית *ke'ilu na'aseh shutaf
l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu bema'aseh Bereishit*. That any judge, you know, if you're
spending all your day sitting in court cases, it doesn't feel like
you're getting the chance to learn too much תורה *Torah*, right? I
mean, you've learned the תורה *Torah* you need to learn, and now
you're spending all your days hearing this guy arguing that this is
what happened, this guy with this is what happened, you know, could
be very sort of like, you know, it does not feel very
religiously satisfying. But the point is, is that no, you're נעשה שותף
להקדוש ברוך הוא במעשה בראשית *na'aseh shutaf l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu bema'aseh Bereishit*.
God created the world. God created the world and you're helping the
world to continue to run, and to continue to run the way
God would have wanted it. So that is part of the message
here, is that it might not personally feel like a religious experience,
but it is exactly a form of תורה. So then it says
וכתיב אידך אפילו תלתא, uch'tiv idach afilu tlata, that's true by three.
עשרה, why do you have to tell me ten? No, עשרה קדים
שכינה ואתיא. asara kadim sh'china v'atya. Ten,
God is already there waiting for you to arrive. God is so
eager for the prayers of a מניין, minyan, of a ציבור, tzibur,
that it's not when you start and then God comes, but it's
that אלוהים ניצב בעדת אל Elohim nitzav ba'adat El when the community
comes. So God is already there ahead of time. ועד
דאתי תלתא v'ad d'ati tlata with three, only once you get in
the activity, then God comes. What's the difference? You know, just that
sense of how important it is, how much it's being anticipated. The
גמרא Gemara actually uses that idea in a minute we'll see about
how the sense of urgency it creates for us. Okay, so אמר
רבי אבין בר אדא אמר רבי יצחק מניין שהקדוש ברוך הוא מניח
תפילין.
amar
Rabbi
Avin bar Adda amar Rabbi Yitzchak minayin she'Hakadosh Baruch Hu meniach tefillin.
Okay,
now we're shifting a little, now that we have that God is
sort of in the shul, we're leaving the building and we're getting
God to actually be one of the, if you were, almost like
one of the מתפללים. mitpalelim. So first we start with how do
we know that God wears תפילין? tefillin? שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse
says, נשבע ה' בימינו ובזרוע עוזו, Nishba Hashem b'yimino u'vizroa uzo,
God takes, swears by His right hand
and by His arm of strength. ימינו זו תורה, yimino zu Torah,
and His right hand is Torah, שנאמר מימינו אשדת למו, shenemar mi'yimino
esh dat lamo, from God's right hand
a fiery covenant for His people. So ובזרוע עוזו, u'vizroa uzo, so
He's holding the תורה in His right hand and He swears by
the
תורה. Now what's the זרוע עוזו? zroa uzo? Presumably that's not the
ימינו, yimino, that's the left hand. So what is God swearing by?
So as opposed to just, you know, God, I'll take your word
for it, it would be enough for God to just not to
hold something. Here's again imagining very anthropomorphically the same way somebody when
they would take an oath would hold a תורה, God is holding
some holy object as well.
I'm confused why תפילין, tefillin, like why God has to wear תפילין.
tefillin.
Oh, is this self-evident? Okay, we'll get to that.
He needs to remember about Himself?
Okay, so good. That's very weird.
And then also like תורה is His word. He doesn't need to
swear by His word. I understand.
Right.
So let's read a little bit more though, those are exactly the
right questions. Let's read a bit more, let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. Okay, so what's the other, the left hand? So you
know you put תפילין tefillin on your left, שנאמר ה' עוז לעמו
יתן, shenemar Hashem oz l'amo yiten,
and God gives עוז oz to His people. So it's something that
He actually gave to His people. He gave תורה and He gave
תפילין, tefillin, part of the, you know, תורה's, תפילין tefillin is contained
in תורה. ומניין שתפילין עוז הם, u'minayin she'tefillin oz hem, and how
do I know that exactly to identify עוז oz with תפילין? tefillin?
I see it's something that God gave to us. How do I
know it's תפילין? tefillin? לישראל. l'Yisrael. דכתיב וראו כל עמי הארץ כי
שם ה' נקרא עליך ויראו ממך. d'chtiv v'rau kol amei ha'aretz ki
shem Hashem nikra alecha v'yaru mimeka. All the people will see that
God's name is called upon you and they will fear you. So
that sense that it's עוז, oz, something of strength, something that gives
us status, that's implicit in that פסוק. pasuk ותניא, v'tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, Baraita, רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר אלו תפילין שבראש. Rabbi
Eliezer haGadol omer elu tefillin she'barosh. These are the זרוע... zroa... right,
I know. So it's not only the תפילין שבראש. tefillin she'barosh. So
תוספות Tosafot thinks that the תפילין שבראש tefillin she'barosh
specifically because God's name is called on us, כי שם ה', ki
shem Hashem, and the תפילין שבראש tefillin she'barosh has the שין shin
embedded in the sort of in the בית, you know, and the
דלת dalet formed by the knot in the back. But then
תוספות Tosafot rejects that interpretation because the גמרא Gemara makes it clear
that the רצועות retzuot are called תשמישי קדושה tashmishei kedusha and they're
not actually קדושה, kedusha, meaning not, excuse me, that the רצועות retzuot
do not have the same קדושה, kedusha, right, they're תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei
kedusha,
they're not a דבר שבקדושה davar she'bikdusha itself. Meaning if you have
something that has God's name written on it like the קלפים, klafim,
that's like a real sort of object of קדושה. kedusha. You have
something that attends to, serves as it were those קלפים, klafim, like
the בית in which the קלפים klafim are housed, that's תשמישי קדושה.
tashmishei kedusha. So תוספות Tosafot says that if we actually considered the
דלת dalet of the רצועות retzuot to be a real written letter
of God's name, it wouldn't just be תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei kedusha, it
would really be an object of קדושה kedusha itself, and it's clear
that the בית has greater status because of the שין shin on
it than the רצועות. retzuot. So he actually says the דלת dalet
on the רצועות retzuot halachically that does not have a status as
a letter of God's name, and that really what the גמרא Gemara
is just saying is that כי שם ה' נקרא עליך, ki shem
Hashem nikra alecha, תוספות Tosafot says, because you know they're very high
up on the head and it's ויראו, v'yaru, you see God's name,
you know, in the sense that it's visible, whereas תפילין tefillin of
the hand, it says from another דרשה drasha is that it's supposed
to be more hidden, that you actually cover it over, you know,
with your sleeve and so on, and anyway just physically on the
body it's more hidden. So when it says they see God's name,
it's not because of the שין דלת, shin dalet, the דלת dalet
he says is not halachically so significant as a letter of God's
name, but it's just that the תפילין tefillin is very visible. Mike
is right, it's the head תפילין, tefillin, but nevertheless it's part of
the whole package. So whatever. Okay, anyway, that's how you get the
תפילין. tefillin. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to continue with similar questions
as we were just asked, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק לרב חייא בר אבין:
Amlei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak l'Rav Chiya bar Avin: הני תפילין דמרי
עלמא מה כתיב בהו? Hani tefillin d'marei alma mai ketiv behu? What's
written in God's תפילין? tefillin? I know what's written in our תפילין.
tefillin. What's written in God's תפילין? tefillin? So the גמרא Gemara says
אמר ליה, amlei, he said: ומי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ. U'mi
k'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz. So who is like your nation Israel,
one nation in the... on the earth? So the same way we
say שמע ישראל השם אלוקינו השם אחד—the Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem
Echad גמרא Gemara makes this sort of like
explicit—we say שמע ישראל השם אלוקינו השם אחד. Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu
Hashem Echad. So what we do is we pronounce God's oneness, and
not only God's oneness in like an objective sense that there's only
one God, there are no other gods, but often it's... some people
suggest that a better translation of the word אחד there is not
God is one, but God alone. God is our God, God alone.
Only God is our God; we have no other gods but God.
Okay, and that that's the אחד. And that way it really parallels
ומי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ. U'mi k'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz.
It's not like there's only one nation on the earth, but גוי
אחד goy echad means like the one chosen nation, the one nation
that God has a unique relationship with. So therefore it's an exact
parallel as us declaring God and our unique relationship with God, and
God now essentially wears תפילין tefillin and doing the same for us.
It's not over. Let's read a little bit more and we'll take
a step back. It says like this: ומי משתבח קודשא בריך הוא
בשבחא דישראל? U'mi mishtabach Kudsha Brich Hu b'shivcha d'Yisrael?
And does God really praise himself with the praises of Israel or
sing the praises of Israel? אין, In, yes! דכתיב: Dichativ: את השם
האמרת היום. Et Hashem hemarta hayom. And here's a פסוק pasuk: in
דברים Devarim which really speaks exactly to this idea. You have sort
of chosen or elevated God today. And then the end of the
פסוק is והשם האמירך היום, V'Hashem hemircha hayom, and God has chosen
and designated and elevated you today. So it's exactly this parallel that
is going on in this sense of you wear תפילין, tefillin, God
wears תפילין. tefillin. So אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל, Amar lehem
Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Yisrael, this is God says to Israel: אתם עשיתוני
חטיבה אחת בעולם. Atem asituni chativa achas ba'olam. You have made me
like one, you know, chosen unit in the world. That's the השם
אחד, Hashem Echad, right? Again, one and the only one. ואני אעשה
אתכם חטיבה אחת בעולם. V'ani e'eseh etchem chativa achas ba'olam. I will
make you the one, sort of special chosen unit in the world.
עשיתוני חטיבה אחת בעולם, Asituni chativa achas ba'olam, if you haven't gotten
the point: שמע ישראל השם אלוקינו השם אחד. Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu
Hashem Echad. ואני אעשה אתכם חטיבה אחת בעולם, V'ani e'eseh etchem chativa
achas ba'olam, I will make you the one chosen unit in the
world, שנאמר: shene'emar, ומי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ. U'mi k'amcha Yisrael
goy echad ba'aretz.
Now, so we get that, you know, this idea that, so that's
question what's written in it? And there's something I think very beautiful
about this about, you know, that the same way we every day
wear something physical to sort of that becomes sort of almost like
part of our identity. It's also the part of what wearing, you
know, clothes and wearing and the power of תפילין tefillin is not
just, a, that it's sort of physically embodied, but also that it's
sort of, you know, it's a לבוש. levush. It's something that identifies
us in terms of וראו. v'ra'u. They see you, they see God's
name called upon you. That now we're sort of imagining the same
thing in terms of God. Now obviously God, you know, in God's
essence, you know, transcends, you know, is sort of the God of
the entire universe, but in some ways the לבוש levush that God
is wearing, the clothes that God is wearing is something that sort
of identifies God and his unique relationship, you know, to us and
to Israel. So the I think that there's something, you know, that's
really very beautiful and powerful about that image. Now of course the
other thing that it does though is, well first of all it
doesn't really fully explain why God can't just swear, why he has
to hold the תפילין tefillin and the תורה in order to swear.
So and that I think I don't have a really like great
answer to that other than that the other obvious thing going on
here is tremendous anthropomorphism, which is and part of the power it's
in this context is, you know, which maybe is part of the
power of anthropomorphism in general, you know, is that it it sort
of on the one hand makes us able to sort of relate
to God better. And on the other hand it brings I think
real power, and I think this is more of what it does,
real power into the religious activity that we do. You know, so
if God swears by his by the תורה when God needs to
swear, then when we swear by the תורה, you know, there's something
that is that much even weightier about that act of swearing by
the תורה, that that's even what God does when God has to
swear. You know, or if we if we wear תפילין, tefillin, well
if God wears תפילין, tefillin, you know, somehow everything we're doing here
is paralleling what God what God is doing in terms of religious
activity. I think it gives it, you know, that much more resonance
and weight. It also, of course like general anthropomorphisms in general, if
you think about God walking around wearing a טלית tallit and תפילין
tefillin and swearing by a תורה, it becomes a much more relatable
way to relate to God. But for some people that's the problem
of anthropomorphism, it's a little bit, you know, too human and too
relatable. Yes.
What about all the other people that are not Jewish? I mean
how does God relate to...
Well that's right. That's the general question. I mean this is obviously
picking up, you know, in דברים, Devarim, you know, obviously throughout the
תורה at הר סיני, Har Sinai, you know, you know, עם סגולה
מכל העמים תחת כל השמים, am segulah mikol ha'amim tachat kol hashamayim,
but in דברים Devarim in particular the whole... sense of God choosing
us, us choosing God, a unique relationship that doesn't include the non-Jews
is very dominant and very much
being emphasized here. And look, this is an ongoing issue that on
the one hand, very much the sense of עם סגולה Am Segula
and
בחירת ישראל, Bechirat Yisrael, the chosen status, and on the other sense,
God is a God for all people, and that both of those
things are true. So the גמרא Gemara here is not working to
resolve that.
Yes,
the גמרא Gemara is just trying to maybe shed a little more
light on this. If you just look at the, because we're saying
God's swearing, what is he swearing? Look at the פסוק in ישעיהו:
Yeshayahu: נשבע ה' בימינו ובזרוע עזו אם אתן את דגנך עוד מאכל
לאויביך. Nishba Hashem biyemino uvizroa uzo im eten et deganech od maachal
leoivech. So
it's a פסוק specifically about בני ישראל, in other words, that we
no longer have all your produce spoiled by your enemies. So that's
kind of why we're bringing this in here.
In other words, which is
why we
have God's תפילין Tefillin מי כעמך ישראל. Mi k'amcha Yisrael. That's why
he's swearing by that.
Maybe, I think let's keep on in the גמרא Gemara though. I
don't think the גמרא Gemara limits it to that, but maybe you
are right that at least certainly in that case when Israel is
oppressed, that sense certainly comes out very much. So let's see how
the גמרא Gemara continues. It says like this:
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara isn't done though. תינח בחד ביתא
שאר
בתי מאי. Tenach b'chad beita, shear batei mai. So the פסוקים Psukim
almost seem like a little reductio ad absurdum what's sometimes in the
process of, meaning okay, that's what's in one of the compartments, but
the other four compartments, what are in the other compartments of God's
תפילין? Tefillin? So on the one hand it's almost like it was
hard enough for me to talk about God's תפילין, Tefillin, I have
to talk about all the other compartments. But by doing that, almost
the גמרא Gemara makes you
naturalize, like okay, fine, God wears תפילין, Tefillin, now let's figure out
what the other compartments are. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, so here's
what it says, here's what's in God's תפילין, Tefillin, the other compartments.
Number one, כי מי גוי גדול, Ki mi goy gadol, who is
a great nation like Israel?
ומי גוי גדול Umi goy gadol אשר לו אלהים קרובים אליו? asher
lo Elohim krovim eilav? All these פסוקים Psukim from דברים Devarim which
speak about the praise of Israel and its relationship to God, as
we're talking about very much about the chosen status. אשריך ישראל, Ashrecha
Yisrael, praised are you Israel, מי כמוך, mi kamocha, who is like
you?
עם נושע בה', Am nosha b'Hashem, a people saved by God. או
הניסה אלהים לבוא לקחת לו גוי מקרב גוי, O hanissa Elohim lavo
lakachat lo goy mikerev goy, has God ever done something so astounding
to take one nation out of another nation as God has done
for you? ולתתך עליון, Uletitcha elyon, to put you supreme over all
the other nations. So again, all these פסוקים, Psukim, they're all taken
from דברים Devarim as you can see, it's a very heavy theme
in דברים Devarim about us being chosen, elevated from the other nations,
unique in our relationship to God. All of this is in God's
תפילין. Tefillin. I know, fine. The גמרא Gemara figured that out. אי
הכי נפישי להו טובא. Ei hachi nefishei lehu tuva. God, you have
too many compartments! אלא, Ela, okay, here's how we're going to get
only four. כי מי גוי גדול Ki mi goy gadol and ומי
גוי גדול Umi goy gadol דדמיין להדדי. dedamyan l'hadadi. Who is a
great nation and who's a great nation? Anyway, those are pretty similar
to one another, בחד ביתא, b'chad beita, that's in one compartment. אשריך
ישראל Ashrecha Yisrael and ומי כעמך ישראל, Umi k'amcha Yisrael, praised are
you Israel, who is like you the nation Israel? בחד ביתא, b'chad
beita, that's pretty similar, that's in another compartment. Okay,
that's sort of being chosen, the other's about being great. או הניסה
אלהים O hanissa Elohim בחד ביתא, b'chad beita, has God ever done
this to take one nation out of another, which is specifically about
the event of the Exodus, that's in another compartment. ולתתך עליון, Uletitcha
elyon, to make you supreme over all the other nations, בחד ביתא,
b'chad beita, that is in another compartment. That's your four compartments. וכולהו
כתיבי באדרעיה. V'chulhu ktivei b'adrayei. And the same way they're all in
the
תפילין של ראש Tefillin shel Rosh which has the פסוק about God's
name, כי שם ה' נקרא עליך, Ki shem Hashem nikra alecha, anyway,
there's four compartments, they're also all in the תפילין של יד Tefillin
shel Yad except there there's only one compartment, but all the same
פרשיות Parshiyot are there. Okay, that is interesting. We are going to
get back to God wearing תפילין Tefillin and doing other similar activities
in a minute, but let's continue now that our focus is on
the שול Shul and God's presence in the שול. Shul. It was
interesting that it shifted because this next statement fits right into the
idea of when people come that God is present in the שול.
Shul. So let's take a look. אמר רבין בר רב אדא אמר
רבי יצחק Amar Rabin bar Rav Adda amar Rabbi Yitzchak כל הרגיל
לבוא לבית הכנסת. kol haragil lavo l'veit haknesset.
By the way, I should say though, the actual transition is אלהים
נצב בעדת אל, Elohim nitzav ba'adat El, God is standing, he's not
standing over, he's not just present, he's standing with the congregation, suggests
that he is right there as an equal participant. So that is
sort of what I think suggested the next shift into this discussion
about God's תפילין Tefillin because we're having God really present directly standing
among us, not hovering among us, standing among us. So then he
talks about God wearing the תפילין Tefillin and that's the theme we'll
come back to. But all of this is about God present in
the שול. Shul. So אמר רבין בר רב אדא אמר רבי יצחק
כל הרגיל לבוא לבית הכנסת ולא בא יום אחד, Amar Rabin bar
Rav Adda amar Rabbi Yitzchak kol haragil lavo l'veit haknesset velo ba
yom echad, anybody
that generally comes to שול Shul and doesn't come one day. Remember,
God is waiting there in שול Shul for people to come, so
he's waiting, he's checking out who's there and who's not. So if
you normally come and one day you're not there, הקדוש ברוך הוא
משאיל בו, Hakadosh Baruch Hu mash'il bo, God says, hey, whatever happened
to פלוני Ploni here, where is he? He usually comes today.
So שנאמר, Shene'emar, the פסוק says, מי בכם ירא ה' שומע בקול
עבדו. Mi vachem yerei Hashem shome'a bekol avdo. So who is it
that you that fears God, listens to the voice of God's servant,
אשר, so normally you're here, you're fearing God, the מהרש"א says listen
to the voice of His servant, the שליח ציבור, shliach tzibbur, who's
the who's the עבדו, avdo, but whatever it means, who's normally here
that fears God, אשר הלך חשכים, asher halach chasheichim, now he's gone
off into the darkness ואין נגה לו, v'ein nogah lo, there's no
light for
him. אם לדבר מצוה הלך, im lid'var mitzvah halach, so God forbid
what happened to him? If it were that he was going on
doing a מצוה, mitzvah so נגה לו, nogah lo, so מצוה mitzvah
we say is like light, so then it's not bad, then he's
going on a path of light. ואם לדבר רשות הלך, ve'im lid'var
reshus halach, if however it's something that's not a מצוה, presumably, you
know, maybe he's doing a making a to a פרנסה, parnassah, he
has to go early for a business meeting or something, then אין
נגה לו, ein nogah lo, it won't be light for him. יבטח
בשם ה', yivtach b'shem Hashem, the end of the פסוק is, have
faith in the name of God in the name of God. מאי
טעמא, mai ta'ama, why is it not the right thing to do?
משום דהוה ליה לבטח בשם ה' ולא בטח, mishum d'hava lei livtoach
b'shem Hashem v'lo batach, because if it's about money, it's about earning
a having a you know making a living, so stay, come back
to דאוון, pray better or pray, and that's how you'll do well
in business. Don't not come to שול shul because you have some
business meeting, you should have had faith in the name of God.
Now it's a fascinating I have to tell you because it speaks
to like a reality, but it's a you know it's like the
reality that it's something that could be questioned. Like so how about
everybody else, the other 95% of the people in this community that
are never in שול shul in the morning? God isn't asking about
them, they're doing whatever they're doing, fine, no expectations about the rest
of you guys. But the guy that's always in שול, shul, you
know, he that raises the expectation, I see what you're committed to,
I see you're a regular שול shul goer, so when you're not
there, I'm very disappointed in you. So it's like really interesting that
that person God gets upset about, but in a way you know
there's something nice about God being upset. He cares enough to be
upset and He has these different expectations of the person that's always
coming to שול shul and one day didn't come than the people
that sort of never come to שול. shul. Yes.
It's like when like משה Moshe sins. Right, exactly,
right.
הקדוש ברוך הוא מדקדק עם חסידיו כחוט השערה. HaKadosh Baruch Hu medakdek
im chasidav k'chut hasa'arah. But this isn't even if this guy isn't
a חסיד chasid more than more of a צדיק tzaddik than other
people, it's not even in general you're on a higher level, but
sometimes you're engaged in certain activities that create expectations that you know
that you'll continue to be doing those things. So it's it's interesting,
right? How come you how come you pick on me? How about
everybody else who's never here? So yes.
Does the same thing be limited to men?
Well that's true also, oh thank you for saying that. Meaning yes,
the מנין, minyan even when it discussed the מנין, minyan it said
ten, it didn't say ten men. Yet these discussions are, look on
the one hand they're very gender neutral, on the other hand they
tend to, the גמרא Gemara even when it's completely gender neutral tends
to assume that we're talking with men or about men. But you're
right that it does not say it. The discussions are you know
are definitely are gender neutral. So now the גמרא Gemara continues, אמר
רב יוחנן בשעה שהקדוש ברוך הוא בא בבית הכנסת. Amar Rav Yochanan
besha'ah sheHaKadosh Baruch Hu ba b'veit hakeneset. So God showed, so He's
concerned if we're going to be making a מנין minyan, and where
are people? Anyway now let him come to the שול shul ולא
מצא בה עשרה, v'lo matza bah asarah, and He came and there
is not yet already a מנין minyan there. Now of course it
said before that God is there waiting for a מנין, minyan so
I don't even know how he's he's always going to get there
a מנין minyan there. But presumably it means let's say God shows
up exactly when מנין minyan is called for. He comes at 8:15
and people are straggling in, there's six people, seven people, you're waiting,
whatever. So God came and there's not a מנין minyan, here, so
מיד כועס, miyad ko'es, He gets angry ולא מצא בה עשרה מיד
הוא כועס. v'lo matza bah asarah miyad hu ko'es. שנאמר מדוע באתי
ואין איש קראתי ואין עונה. she'ne'emar madua basi v'ein ish karasi v'ein
oneh. I came but nobody was here, right? Called out and there
was none to answer. So if מנין minyan, is called for a
particular time, again God's sort of expectations, you know you're not there,
God gets really annoyed that He came and people aren't ready to
get started. I think I think we could all I think we're
all identify when people come to a מנין, minyan. it takes time
to get a מנין, minyan? it's like I showed up on time,
right? These these two reactions are very much reactions about people that
are waiting to get a מנין. minyan? Where is that guy? He's
always here, why isn't he here today? How come nobody's here, but
then you know it's nine o'clock, where's the מנין? minyan Anyway, but
this idea... what? Yeah, exactly. And does He count for a מנין?
minyan
I will say this this idea
of God getting upset that there isn't a מנין minyan. is actually
used in one place by one of the ראשונים rishonim because there's
a famous גמרא that we're going to get to that that there
was that they needed a מנין minyan. and right and there was
there was who else was it? טבי? Tevvi? No. It was טבי?
Tevvi? Yes, anyway, so טבי Tevvi was a slave, was there, but
he couldn't count for a מנין. minyan. So he was freed in
order to make a מנין. So the ראשונים rishonim ask but you
know according to another גמרא you're not allowed to free your slaves.
Why was that allowed? So it says well, so the רמב"ן Ramban
says since if ten people are there and God comes and aren't
ten people there and God gets angry, so it's such an overriding
of importance that it even allowed him to transgress this prohibition or
this מצוה of not freeing slaves. So that obviously raises other questions,
what's this מצוה of not freeing slaves and whatever, but anyway the
point being though that some ראשונים rishonim took this not as an
אגדתא statement but even something that actually has הלכה halakhah weight in
terms of the importance of a מנין. So now the גמרא continues,
אמר רבי חלבו אמר רב הונא. Amar Rabbi Chelbo amar Rav Huna.
כל הקובע מקום לתפלתו. Kol hakovei'a makom litfillato.
Now we're sort of talking, we talked about בית כנסת beit knesset.
and God in the בית כנסת. beit knesset Now we're talking about
having a מקום קבוע, makom kavua, a fixed place. Anybody who has
a fixed place for his prayer, אלהי אברהם בעזרו, Elohei Avraham be'ezro,
the God of אברהם Avraham is at his
aid. And when he dies, they say over him at a הספד,
hesped, אי ענו אי חסיד, Ei anav, ei chasid, where is the,
you know, the humble person, where's the righteous person, you know, who
passed away, מתלמידיו של אברהם אבינו, mitalmidav shel Avraham Avinu, from the
students of Abraham Avinu. Now that thing, אי ענו אי חסיד, Ei
anav, ei chasid, as we have other evidence or whatever, was like
a classic trope in liturgy, not in liturgy, in eulogy, that they
did
at the time of חז"ל. Chazal, So actually it says this is
something that you say for people that are very sort of have,
you know, serious about their דאוונען davening and have a fixed מקום
קבוע makom kavua for their
דאוונען. davening. אברהם אבינו מנלן דקבע מקום, Avraham Avinu minalan dekava makom,
where do you know that Abraham had a מקום קבוע? makom kavua?
דכתיב וישכם אברהם בבקר אל המקום אשר עמד שם, Dechtiv vayashkem Avraham
baboker el hamakom asher amad sham,
Abraham got up and stood at the place where he had stood
before. So there's this thing of going back to the same place.
ואין עמידה אלא תפלה, Ve'ein amidah ela tefillah,
standing doesn't just mean standing, it means praying, שנאמר ויעמד פינחס ויפלל,
Shene'emar vaya'amod Pinchas vayipalel,
פינחס Pinchas stood and he ויפלל, vayipalel, which could be judged or
whatever, but here we're reading to mean ויתפלל, vayitpallel, that he prayed.
So two comments about this. Number one, מקום קבוע makom kavua is
independent of בית כנסת. beit knesset, You know, it's even if a
person doesn't go to the שול shul for whatever reason, far away,
he's not well, whatever other reasons he doesn't go to שול, shul,
there's still the idea of having a מקום קבוע, makom kavua, a
fixed place. So it's not exactly, not necessarily the same conversation as
the בית כנסת beit knesset, conversation.
Number one. Number two is, I mean, we certainly know the, you
know, מקום קבוע, makom kavua, that that's been a big issue, you
know, even in like in issues of like, you know, that have
been like debated and come to בית דין about like where was,
you know, you were in my, you know, that's my מקום, makom,
it's not your מקום, makom, you're not allowed to be here, and
so on. We know for example when a person sits שבעה, shivah,
that they have to, you know, move, change their place. So there's
a real sense of מקום קבוע. makom kavua. Actually, somebody once told
me, Rabbi Berman told me, you know, that he goes to דאוונען
daven at like
Ramat Orai in the city. And there was one שבת Shabbos where
his wife Shelly was up in the women's section and there was
like three women in the entire women's section. And one woman comes
over to her to, excuse me, you're in my
place.
So of 700 people and there were three dozen people there and
someone tells me I'm in their place.
So the significance of it, it's not to be treated, I mean,
obviously there's a בין אדם לחברו bein adam lachaveiro aspect as well,
but the significance is really important. You know, if you have, it
means you don't do this thing haphazardly. Oh, today I'm going to
דאוונען daven here, tomorrow דאוונען daven there. Like there's a sense of
you, you know, when you have a fixed place, there's an identity,
we tend to be territorial, right? We tend to be, as you
see, but we have a sense, like this is my place, this
is where I belong, and you know, and a sense of sort
of your relationship to God, that there's sort of, we also make
associations when, you know, with places. If we're at all, so that
we continue to sort of, it becomes very much associated with our
history of דאוונען davening there and our experience of דאוונען davening there
and the fixed nature of that type of a relationship. So I
think there's something very powerful about that aspect of מקום קבוע. makom
kavua. Yes.
I always felt that this was overly taken overly literally and you
could just as well say that you have a regular place to
go, like this is the שול shul I go to, this is
the mountaintop that I climb to דאוונען. daven. Uh-huh.
You mean not the narrow place, the particular chair.
And then the הלכה halakha. literature is probably full of exactly how
far you can be, but to take a שול.
shul. Right. I
maybe, I'm not so sure. I mean, it says אברהם אל המקום
אשר עמד שם, Avraham el hamakom asher amad sham, הקובע מקום, hakovei'a
makom, you know, we talk about בית כנסת, beit knesset. בית כנסת,
beit knesset it doesn't say הקובע בית כנסת לתפלתו. hakovei'a beit knesset
litfillato. So you know, maybe overly literal in the exact ארבע אמות,
arba amos, but
as he wasn't in a בית כנסת.
beit knesset Maybe, well, right. I understand what you're saying anyway.
I understand.
I hear. Okay. I'm not so sure. I don't think I agree
with that, but I certainly hear that you can interpret this sort
of more as a more broad type of a statement. The aspect
also about אברהם, Avraham, I would say as well, and this is
more sort of symbolically than psychologically, what I was saying before about
the מקום לתפלתו makom litfillato is, you know, there's a sense of
holding your ground, holding your place, and a sense of being like
אברהם Avraham is like the pillar of faith, right? אברהם, Avraham, you
know, constantly had that sense of faith in God and whatever he
did and he went and he fought after the kings and, you
know, everything that happened. אברהם Avraham sort of represents, you know, that
sense of always sort of, you know, holding his ground in terms
of his faith of God and not letting it waver. So I
think that there's maybe something here about the symbolism of being מתלמידיו
של אברהם mitalmidav shel Avraham in that, in sort of that symbolic
sense about what it means to be holding your place in your
relationship to God.
And also Abraham, I mean, that was a time when this whole
area was במחלוקת bemachlokes between him and לוט. Lot. Right. And Abraham
was arguing with God.
Well, that's a good point too. That's an excellent point too. I
was thinking more in general. with a person of faith, but you're
saying in his standing and praying to God, he didn't budge. He
didn't give in easy to God. That's also very nice point that
even when he's even in his prayer with God he's really holding
staying holding his ground. So that's very nice. Thank you. יישר כח.
Yasher koach. So now the גמרא goes on. אמר רבי חלבו אמר
רב הונא. Amar Rabi Chelbo amar Rav Huna. היוצא מבית הכנסת, Ha'yotzei
mi'beit haknesset, so again we're going into your experience in the שול.
shul. When you leave the שול, shul, אל יפסיע פסיעה גסה. al
yifsi'a pesi'ah gassah. Don't take big steps. Don't look like you're in
a rush to go out of שול. shul. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
don't tell all the people that are going to catch Metro North
or something. And I know it's a הלכה. halakha אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, לא אמרן אלא למיפק. lo aman ella le'meifa. That's only when
you're leaving שול. shul. אבל למיעיל, aval le'meito,
but if you are going into שול, shul, מצווה למירהט. mitzvah le'mirhatz.
It's a מצווה mitzvah to run, שנאמר, נרדפה לדעת את ה׳. nirdofah
lada'at et Hashem. Let us run to know God. That's not obvious,
it could just be saying decorum. You shouldn't be, you know, decorum.
You shouldn't be running in שול, shul, you shouldn't be taking big
steps. No, no. It's not about decorum as much as it is
about showing that your hesitancy to depart. And therefore when you're going
into שול shul you can be sort of taking big steps to
get into שול shul quickly. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, רב
זירא Rav Zeira said, מריש כי הוינא חזינא להו לרבנן, me'reish ki
havina chazina lehu le'rabbanan, when I originally saw the rabbis, the רבנן
rabbanan often means like the rabbinic students, דרהטי לפרקא בשבתא, de'rahatei le'pirka
be'shabta,
they were running to hear the דרשה drasha on שבת. Shabbos. אמינא,
Amina, קמחלי רבנן שבתא. kamechallei rabbanan shabbata. I said they're desecrating the
שבת. Shabbos. I mean not that they're doing a מלאכה melacha but
they're desecrating the spirit of שבת, Shabbos, they're running on שבת. Shabbos.
כיון דשמענא להא דרבי תנחום אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Keivan de'shama'ana
le'had Rabi Tanchum amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi, once I heard what
the statement of רבי תנחום Rabi Tanchum that he says, לעולם ירוץ
אדם לדבר הלכה ואפילו בשבת. le'olam yarutz adam lidvar halakha va'afillu be'shabbat.
You should always run to hear, you know, a דבר הלכה. dvar
halakha. Some say לדבר מצווה, lidvar mitzvah, even on שבת. Shabbos. שנאמר,
אחרי ה׳ ילכו כאריה ישאג, acharei Hashem yelechu ke'aryeh yish'ag,
after God they will go he will roar like a lion. So
אנא נמי רהיטנא, ana nami reitna, so I also run even on
שבת. Shabbos. So again there's a parallel, right? שבת Shabbos and the
בית כנסת you would think there's a certain spirit of the day,
a certain decorum of the place that you shouldn't be running regardless.
But no, the idea that you're running towards דבר ה׳, dvar Hashem,
you know, is, you know, even in some way it is a
little bit violating the decorum of the place and a little bit
violating the spirit of שבת. Shabbat. Ultimately that's, you know, the more,
that, you know,
either the more important value and you could even say more than
just more important value, it's even
it's more appropriate to the decorum, you know, and to the spirit
of what שבת Shabbos is about and what בית כנסת is about
to have that experience even if in some way it breaks other
aspects of the decorum. Okay, so that's also a definite הלכה halakha
that you're not supposed to run on שבת, Shabbat, you're not supposed
to take big steps out of a שול, shul, but you can
run to דבר מצווה. dvar mitzvah. Sure run to
שול shul on שבת. Shabbos. You don't have to if you're on
time. I don't think I think you could do both, you don't
have to. You're not supposed to דווקא. davka. אמר רב זירא, Amar
Rav Zeira, אגרא דפרקא, agra de'pirka, now that we're talking about running,
so we continue in this vein. אגרא דפרקא רהטא. agra de'pirka rahata.
The reward for going to the דרשה drasha is the running to
the דרשה, drasha, which basically means that most people don't really understand
it or appreciate it well enough, but at least you know what
is it Woody Allen said, right? 90% of life is just showing
up. So that's what he says. So the reward for going to
the דרשה drasha is running, you know, maybe not even going there,
maybe there everybody's expected to be at the דרשה, drasha, but at
least if you run and you show a little bit of eagerness,
then that's where you get your reward even if you don't really
understand what's being talked about. Right. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אגרא דכלה,
agra de'kalla, the reward of the כלה kalla which was the teaching
of הלכה halacha that was done for the entire ציבור tzibur like,
you know, before before the רגלים, regalim, before the חג. chag. דוחקא.
dukhka. That is the sort of pressure, so many people are there,
it's so crowded and that you're willing to be in this crowded
place, you know, also there's an assumption that exactly we mentioned that
the other day because of the מזיקין. mazikin. But anyway, again interesting
that here he assumes most people they're not getting the reward so
much from what they're hearing and listening, maybe most people don't understand,
but they're getting the reward for being there, for putting up with
with the whole crowds. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, אגרא דשמעתא סברא. agra
de'shma'ta sevara. The reward of שמעתא shma'ta which is after like learning
of תורה and the effort, that comes from, you know, the understanding
that you you sort of that you invest in order to really
try to get the understanding. Meaning other
presumably effort רב אשי Rav Ashi emphasizes the effort, but it's also
the actual you know getting the insight. So it seems that the
shift is that the first two were very public events and pretty
much everybody was expected to be there. So the rabbis maybe were
expecting that a lot of people didn't get so much out of
the content as they did out of the experience. And therefore the
reward is being part of the experience. Whereas שמעתא shma'ta is something
that, you know, תורה scholars engage in. And there, don't think it's
just showing up. There, if you're engaged in it, then it's the
really the effort and the accomplishment, that's the reward. אמר רב פפא,
Amar Rav Papa, אגרא דבי טמיא שתיקותא. agra de'vei tamaya shetikusa. Reward
for going even to a cemetery or a mourner's house, there's a
question which one it means, is silence. So that's very interesting. Cemetery
you understand I think, you know, about the the way you approach
the way your presence, but even in a mourner's house, you know,
obviously there's an idea
of... by a שבעה shiva call, of talking about appropriate things, but
very often people can talk about trivial things, you know, and the
actual the first few days of the שבעה, shiva, the מנחמים menachamim
are not supposed to start the conversation. They're supposed to be there
and be quiet and wait for the mourner to start and to
talk. So sometimes like a quiet presence, attentive quiet presence is more
what's needed than just, you know, running your mouth off and talking
about random things. And sort of appropriate sort of in terms of,
you know, of what that context, of what's appropriate, of what's needed
for that context. So there, being there and being quiet and being
present for the other person, that is what is the true reward.
אמר מר זוטרא, Amar Mar Zutra, אגרא דתעניתא צדקתא. igra d'tanisa tzidkasa.
The reward of the fast day is the צדקה. tzedakah. What does
that mean? So it could just mean like sort of, you know,
the fast is not what's important, it's how it translates into actions
and giving צדקה, tzedakah, but רש"י Rashi also says that the poor
people are really, you know, to give צדקה tzedakah on the fast
day so that the poor people have what to eat after the
end of the fast and for them that they don't eat well
during the rest of the week, there's really suffering from the fast.
And maybe also, I'm adding this, רש"י Rashi doesn't say it, but
now that you fast you understand what it means to be without
food, hopefully that means you'll also be a little more generous in
your צדקה. tzedakah. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshes, אגרא דהספדא דלויי.
igra d'hespeda daluyei. The reward of the הספד, hesped, the eulogy, is
sort of the moaning out, the crying out. In the time of
חז"ל, Chazal eulogies were not so much, maybe they were, but they
were not like primarily like they are for us about sort of
talking about the life of the dead person, like, you know, it
was about, they did that, but it was in the way of
evoking like wailing and crying and that was a very major part
of the experience of the eulogy. אמר רב אשי, Rav Ashi רב
אשי said, אגרא דבי הלולי מילי. igra d'bei hiluli mili. The reward
of the of the place of rejoicing, which would mean here like
a wedding feast, מילי mili is saying words. So רש"י Rashi says
like saying words to help rejoice for the חתן choson and the
כלה kallah and, you know, say very nice things to
them. So I just want to say one other point about the
רש"י Rashi which is that very interesting רש"י Rashi which I like
quoting, which רש"י Rashi which when רש"י Rashi says
אגרא דפרקא, igra d'pirka, it's like a רש"י Rashi about 10 lines
before the bottom on the right hand side, when you're going to
hear the הלכה דרשה, drasha, he says עיקר קבול שכר ביד הרצים
לשמוע דרשה מפי חכם השכר מרוצה, ikar kibul sachar b'yad haratzim lishmoa
drasha mipi chacham hasachar merutzah, to run. כי רובם אינם מבינים, ki
rubam einam mevinim, most people don't understand לחמודי גרסא lachmudi girsa to
really sort of, you know, get what was being taught, ולומר שמועה
מפי רבן לאחר זמן, vlomar shmuah mipi raban l'achar zman, and in
order to say back what they heard after a while. So I
always thought that was a great explanation of what it means to
understand something, that a little while later you can say it back.
Okay, so רש"י Rashi says most people, oh it was such a
great דרשה. drasha. Why, what did he say? I don't remember. Okay,
but at least you were there. Anyway, so now the גמרא goes
on. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, כל המתפלל אחורי בית הכנסת
נקרא רשע. kol hamispallel achorei beis haknesses nikra rasha. Whoever prays behind
the בית הכנסת, beis haknesses, you're in the back row, maybe you're
even outside, different interpretations, you're
wicked. שנאמר, סביב רשעים יתהלכון, saviv reshaim yis'hallechun, that's where the wicked
people walk. So presumably it more likely means outside rather than the
back row, and even so the גמרא is going to qualify it.
אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לא אמרן אלא דלא מהדר אפיה לבי כנישתא.
lo amran ela d'lo mahadar apei l'bei knishta. That's only if you're
not turning your face in the direction of the שול. shul. You're
outside of the שול shul and your back is to the שול,
shul, you're facing in the opposite direction, looks like you're praying and
you're דאוונען. davening. אבל מהדר אפיה לבי כנישתא, aval mahadar apei l'bei
knishta, if you're outside the שול shul and you're praying, you know,
in the same direction as everybody in the שול shul is praying,
לית לן בה, leit lan bah, then it's not as bad as,
you know, not this terrible thing you just said.
But this doesn't apply to your house, it's like, you know, yeah,
yeah, yeah.
ההוא גברא דקמצלי אחורי בי כנישתא ולא מהדר אפיה לבי כנישתא. hahu
gavra d'kamtzallei achorei bei knishta v'lo mahadar apei l'bei knishta. There was
a person that was praying outside of the שול shul and his
was not facing the שול, shul, his back was to the שול,
shul, again it could really, so חליף אליהו, chalif Eliyahu, so אליהו
Eliyahu came. Now some say אליהו Eliyahu doesn't really fit here in
the context and some have other גירסא girsa like a certain nomad,
an Arab nomad is טייעא taya like as a, pass-by,
חזייה, chazyei, saw him. אידמי ליה כטייעא, idme lei k'taya, so according
to this version אליהו Eliyahu appeared like this nomad, or maybe it
actually was this, you know, nomad passing by. אמר ליה, amar lei,
and he said to him: כדו בר קיימת קמיה מרך, kadu bar
kayyams k'mei marach, this is how you're standing in front of your
master? That, you know, everybody's in the שול, shul, you're praying with
your back to the שול, shul, your back to God as it
were? שלף ספסירא וקטליה, shalaf sapsira v'katlei, he drew his sword and
he killed him. And that is the end of that story. אמר
ליה
ההוא מרבנן לרביבי בר
אביי, amar lei hahu merabbanan l'Rav Bibi bar Abaye, one of the
rabbis said to רביבי בר אביי, Rav Bibi bar Abaye, ואמרי ליה
רביבי לרב נחמן בר יצחק, v'amri lei Rav Bibi l'Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak, some say רביבי Rav Bibi said to רב נחמן בר יצחק,
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מאי כרום זלות לבני אדם? mai k'rum zalus
livnei adam? Like the כרום krum of the זלות zalut of something
that is, you know,
degraded to people. I am going to explain it anyway. I'm going
to explain, the גמרא is going to translate it. אמר ליה אלו
דברים שעומדים ברומו של עולם ובני אדם מזלזלים בהן. amar lei elu
devarim sheomdim berumo shel olam uvnei adam mezalzelim bahen. Things that really
belong in the heights of the world, that are of the utmost
importance, and people treat them lightly. So what does that mean? It
means things specifically like prayer. People say כגון תפילה שעולה למעלה, kegon
tefillah she'olah lemala,
which is again, it's very fascinating. Right, we are in ברכות, Berakhot,
so if there's one place in ש"ס Shas where חז"ל are going
to talk about the importance of prayer and not just the importance
about תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah, it's going to be here. And as
I said, there is always this ongoing tension of תפילה and תורה,
but here it's acknowledged you know, some people, "I'll finish דאוונען, davening,
whatever, I'll spend more time learning" or "whatever, I'll spend more time",
they don't give enough weight to דאוונען. davening. And that is ultimately
that so that, you know, that, and that, this is how people
treat it that and they, really it stands ברומו של עולם. berumo
shel olam. רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Elazar
de'amri tarveihu, they both say a different interpretation of this פסוק: כיון
שנצטרך אדם לבריות, keivan shenitzrach adam labriyot, as when a person has
to become, you know, needs the assistance of other people, זלות לפני
אדם, zalut lifnei adam, meaning he becomes sort of lowly to people,
then פניו משתנות ככרום, panav mishtanot k'krum, his his face changes to
look like a כרום, krum, which is some type of a... a
bird? Yeah. What? Does it get...
no,
I don't think it's rust, I think it's some type of a
plant.
Anyway, how do they translate כרום krum there anyway? A bird. A
bird? Oh, I'm sorry, that's right. I was about to say that,
I'm sorry. שנאמר כרום זלות לבני אדם. shene'emar krum zalut livnei adam.
So when you're זלות, zalut, when you become lowly in the eyes
of people, then your face changes colors. מאי כרום? Mai krum? Right,
the גמרא says. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata Rav Dimi
amar, עוף אחד יש בכרכי הים, of echad yesh becharkei hayam, there's
a certain bird in the islands, וכרום שמו, v'krum shemo, called כרום,
krum, וכיון שחמה זורחת v'keivan shechama zorachat מהפך לכמה גוונין, mehapech l'chama
gevanin, when the sun shines, it turns into all these different colors.
Maybe a parrot of some sort? Anyway, so like you, your face,
a person's face will turn into all these different colors once he's
in this situation. רב אמי ורב אסי דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav Ami v'Rav
Assi de'amri tarveihu, they both say, כאילו נידון בשני דינים אש ומים.
ke'ilu nidon bishnei dinim esh u'mayim. If a person needs, you know,
the assistance of people, it feels like you're being judged with two
judgments, water and fire. שנאמר הרכבת אנוש לראשנו באנו באש ובמים, shene'emar
hirkavta enosh leroshinu banu va'esh uvamayim, you have caused people to be
above us,
we have come into fire and water, which presumably means it's not
enough that you have suffered this way in terms of your situation
in life, that you have poor, you don't have the means or
whatever, now you have to suffer at the social level, at the
embarrassment level, that now you have to turn to people for their
assistance. So we will end here as we continue to get more
and more behind.